{"tossups": [{"question": "The losing running mate in this election year ran for President again four years later despite the <em>National Enquirer</em> exposing his affair with Rielle Hunter. This election year\u2019s \u201cOctober surprise\u201d may have been a videotape of Osama bin Laden taunting one candidate as \u201ceasy for us to provoke.\u201d The Swift Boat Veterans for Truth released attack ads in, for ten points, what election year in which John Kerry lost to the re-election campaign of George W. Bush?", "answer": "U.S. Presidential election of<b> 2004</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This event, which may have been started by an attack by Janibeg, re-occurred in the 1850s in China and India, and again in San Francisco in 1900. The Italian city of Pistoia went into isolation during this event, which was marked by the emergence of doctors wearing bird beaks stuffed with sweet smelling flowers. At the time, this event was commonly blamed on Jews poisoning wells, but its true cause was infected fleas. For ten points, name this plague that killed a third of Europe in the 14th century.", "answer": "<b> Black Death</b> (accept<b> Bubonic Plague</b>; accept the<b> Black Plague</b>; prompt on plague)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Gabriel tries to play this instrument, but it makes no sound, at the end of<em> Fences</em> by August Wilson. In 1845, Christophe Ballot assembled two groups of players of this instrument for what may have been the first public demonstration of the Doppler Effect. The \u201cnatural\u201d style of this instrument was popular in the Baroque era, and this instrument didn\u2019t receive its now-common valves until the 20th century. Marching parades and fanfares typically feature, for ten points, what highest standard brass instrument?", "answer": "<b> trumpet</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "During this event, the Twa people were targeted for allegedly aiding the enemy. The Arusha Accords failed to address the tensions leading up to this event, which was mitigated through Operation Turquoise\u2019s creation of a safe zone. The order to \u201ccut down the tall trees\u201d was given during this event, which was perpetrated by the Interahamwe. A Patriotic Front led by Paul Kagame took Kigali to end, for ten points, what 1994 event in which the Hutus slaughtered the Tutsis?", "answer": "<b> Rwanda</b>n<b> genocide</b> (accept descriptive answers of a<b> genocide</b> of the<b> Tutsi</b>s/by the<b> Hutu</b>s before either is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Council of Pisa failed to end this period by electing Alexander V. This period was ended by a council that also ordered the execution of Jan Hus, and it began with the election of Clement VII in 1378. The election of Martin V at the Council of Constance brought an end to this period, which included the rule of Benedict XIII as Antipope. For ten points, name this period from 1378 to 1417 in which multiple popes reigned simultaneously from Rome and Avignon.", "answer": "<b> Western Schism</b> (accept<b> Schism of 1378</b> before \u201c1378\u201d is mentioned; accept<b> Great Occidental Schism</b>, but do not prompt on \u201cGreat Schism\u201d alone; accept<b> Papal Schism</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man, who fled to Crown Point after a battle in which his ships were destroyed by Guy Carleton, spread rumors that his force approaching Fort Stanwix was much larger than it really was. After the Battle of Lake Champlain, this husband of Peggy Shippen prompted Benjamin Franklin to scowl \u201cJudas sold only one man,\u201d but this man \u201c[sold] three million.\u201d For ten points, name this Revolutionary War general who tried to betray West Point to the British.", "answer": "Benedict<b> Arnold</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A father and son of the Roebling family designed this structure over the East River. For ten points, name this bridge that links a namesake Long Island borough to Manhattan.", "answer": "<b> Brooklyn Bridge</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "This state promoted a traditional view of motherhood, one of many conservative reforms promoted as National Regeneration. A paramilitary group in this state called the<em> Milice</em> was headed by its Prime Minister, Pierre Laval. This state\u2019s ships were attacked by the British while stationed at Mers el K\u00b4ebir and were scuttled in Toulon. This state revolved around the popularity of its president, Marshal Philippe Pet\u00b4ain. For ten points, name this puppet state that was established by the Nazis after the fall of France.", "answer": "<b> Vichy</b> France (accept<b> French State</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1999, this country sought to isolate Ladakh and force its enemies to withdraw from the Siachen Glacier by launching Operation Badr, even though it had committed to the peaceful Lahore Declaration in the same year. This country\u2019s troops crossed the Line of Control to instigate the Kargil War against a rival with whom it often contests the region of Kashmir. For ten points, name this rival and western neighbor of India.", "answer": "<b> Pakistan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This substance was recklessly handled by factory owners in cities like Waterbury, Connecticut, Orange, New Jersey, and Ottawa, Illinois, where workers were given the instructions \u201clip, dip, paint.\u201d In 1921, President Harding presented Marie Curie with a vial holding one gram of this substance, which names an institute she led at the University of Paris. After polonium, this was the second element discovered by the Curies. For ten points, name this highly toxic radioactive element with chemical symbol Ra [spell it].", "answer": "<b> radium</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man, who was discovered lurking in the woods by Benjamin Phipps, is discussed as an inspiration in the autobiography of Henry \u201cBox\u201d Brown. Jim Travis was one of the targets of an event organized by this man, who was inspired by the viewing of a solar eclipse. This man lived in Southampton County, where he was inspired by Denmark Vesey to carry out an attack that resulted in roughly 60 deaths. For ten points, name this leader of an 1831 slave rebellion.", "answer": "Nat<b> Turner</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This recipient of the 1990 Nobel Peace Prize pulled out of a prolonged conflict in (*)</b> Afghanistan and introduced the perestroika reforms. For ten points, name this last premier of the USSR.", "answer": "Mikhail<b> Gorbachev</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Artemis Ward ordered colonial militia to fortify the area surrounding this city. Cannons captured at Fort Ticonderoga were brought to the Dorchester Heights outside of this city by Henry Knox in the Noble Train of Artillery. (+) Israel Putnam likely gave the order \u201cDon\u2019t fire until you see the whites of their eyes\u201d in a battle fought near this city. Skirmishes at (*) </b>Lexington and Concord preceded a siege of, for ten points, what Massachusetts city that was the site of the Battle of Bunker Hill?", "answer": "<b> Boston</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In 1999, this country\u2019s town of Magdalena was hit by the largest freshwater oil spill in history. This country\u2019s Mar Chiquita, or Little Sea, is found in its Cordoba province. In the</b> <b>1980s, this country initially complained about the construction of the (+)</b> <b>Itaipu Dam on</b> <b>the border of two of its neighbors because the dam threatened the flow of the Parana River, which empties into the Rio de la Plata between this country and (*)</b> Paraguay. For ten points, name this South American country where, in 1536, Spanish conquistadors founded Buenos Aires.", "answer": "<b> Argentina</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}